Finding Aid for Interfraternity Council (University of Michigan) records, 1912-1994
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Interfraternity Council (University of Michigan) records 1912-1994, 1960-1992
University of Michigan. Interfraternity Council.
3 linear feet
87204 Bimu F45 2
The Inter-fraternity Council (IFC) is the administrative and organizing body for the undergraduate social fraternities at the University of Michigan. Records include meeting minutes, officers reports, newspaper clippings, photographs, printed materials. One bound volume of handwritten meeting minutes from 1912-1930, provides the only record of earliest activities of the IFC.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The majority of the records of the Interfraternity Council (Donor no. 442 ) were transferred in May 1994.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
The Interfraternity Council (IFC) is the administrative and organizing body for the undergraduate social fraternities at the University of Michigan. The IFC was developed out of a need to provide a governing body for the fraternity system.
Beta Theta Pi and Chi Psi are credited with being the first fraternities on campus, both established at the University of Michigan in 1846. Over the next sixty some years, several unsuccessful attempts were made by the university administration to govern the growing fraternity system, all of which were met with student resistance. However, the need for some sort of governing body was recognized, due to decreasing ideals of scholarship in the fraternities, members being pledged long before they were ready for college, and questionable methods used in "rushing" prospective members (The University of Michigan: An Encyclopedic Survey, p. 1804). Although a group had been meeting informally since 1912, the Interfraternity Conference was organized in 1914, following a recommendation contained in a report by the Committee on Student Affairs presented in 1913.
The first IFC constitution (1914) included the following provisions: all pledging must be done in Ann Arbor; no pledging permitted before the tenth day prior to the starting of class; no freshmen allowed to live in the fraternity house; no initiate should have less than 11 credit hours of at least a C grade; and no student on probation or warning should be initiated.
The IFC developed and enforced regulations for the conduct of fraternity affairs such as rushing, pledging, and dances. At one time the judiciary committee of the IFC was the governing body for fraternity students. In 1924, the name of the Interfraternity Conference was changed to the Interfraternity Council.
The IFC's initial organization consisted of two delegates from each fraternity, and an executive committee composed of elected officers and the Dean of Students. The number of delegates per house gradually decreased from two to one, and the role of the Dean of Students diminished with the creation of the IFC Coordinator position in the 1970s.
Currently, the IFC meets biweekly to discuss matters of importance to all fraternities, including Rush, Greek Week, social activities, academic requirements, and community relations. From the 1940s to the 1960s, the IFC was heavily involved in the issues surrounding membership selection and was instrumental in requiring mandatory non-discrimination clauses in all fraternity house rushing rules.
The records of the Interfraternity Council (IFC) measure 3 linear feet and date from 1912 to 1994, with the bulk of records falling between 1960 and 1994. The records consist of meeting minutes, officer's reports, newspaper clippings, photographs, and printed materials. Despite the range of years covered by the collection as a whole, no one time period is completely documented. For additional information on the IFC, the researcher should consult the record groups under "University of Michigan Fraternity Office" and "University of Michigan Housing Division" and the "University of Michigan Vice President for Student Affairs" at the Bentley Historical Library.
The records of the IFC are divided into five series: President's Notebooks, Fraternity Membership Selection Files, Topical Files, Photographs, and Printed Materials.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Interfraternity Conference.; University of Michigan. Interfraternity Council.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; Greek letter societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan. Interfraternity Council.; Fraternities and sororities--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Buildings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Student housing.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Buildings.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1981-1990.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- President's Notebooks
  The President's Notebooks series (.5 linear feet) consists of materials dating from 1985/86 to 1987/88 and 1990/91 to 1991/92. The records are composed of materials compiled by the presidents of IFC, and originally maintained in notebooks. Materials include meeting minutes, executive agendas, officer lists, the IFC constitution, correspondence, and information documenting issues of importance to the IFC. Although the level of documentation is uneven, these records are one of the best sources of information on IFC activities and policies.
  - 1985/86 (Box 1)
  - 1986/87, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1987/88 (Box 1)
  - 1990/91 (Box 1)
  - 1991/92, 3 folders (Box 1)
- Fraternity Membership Selection Files 1945-1967
  The Fraternity Membership Selection Files series (1 linear foot) consists of materials dating from 1945 to 1967, documenting membership selection policies in fraternities and discriminatory practices in pledging. The IFC was especially active during this period in establishing and enforcing non-discriminatory clauses in individual fraternity house pledging rules. Also included in this series are folders on the Student Government Council, the Committee on Membership in Student Organizations, and the Panhellenic Membership Committee as they relate to this issue. There are four folders of general material that provide a historical context, documenting this issue at the University of Michigan and nationally.
  - General 1945-1967, undated, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Chi Psi 1965 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Membership in Student Organizations
    - Meeting Minutes 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Delta Chi 1989 (Box 1)
  - Disaffiliation of Fraternities and Sororities at the University of Michigan 1964 (proposed by Regent Allan R. Sorenson) (Box 1)
  - Exempt Campus Organizations 1964 (Box 1)
  - Fraternity Bias Procedures and Fair Housing 1963 (letters from Prof. Robert J. Harris) (Box 1)
  - IFC Membership Committee 1959-1965 (Box 1)
  - Membership Recommendation Policies 1963-1964, undated (Box 1)
  - Newsclippings
    - 1959-1962 (Box 1)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Panhellenic Membership Committee 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Phi Delta Theta 1961, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Sigma Nu Support Letters 1962 (Box 1)
  - Student Government Council (SGC)
    - Correspondence
      - General 1960-1965 (Box 1)
      - Fraternities and Sororities 1960-1962 (Box 1)
    - First Membership Council, May 1960-Fall 1963 (Box 1)
    - Fraternity and Sorority Statements 1960-1964 (Box 1)
    - Legalities and Regulations 1963, undated (Box 1)
    - Membership Committee Meeting Minutes 1964-1965 (Box 2)
    - Membership Selection Rules 1963 (Box 2)
    - Reports to SGC from Committee on Membership in Student Organizations 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - TRIGON 1964-1965 (Box 2)
  - Waiver Policies 1962, undated (Box 2)
  - Zeta Beta Tau 1965 (Box 2)
- Topical Files 1912-1993
  The Topical Files series (1.5 linear feet) is arranged alphabetically and consists primarily of materials relating to the activities of the IFC within the university's Greek system. The largest group of records consists of IFC meeting minutes, including a bound volume of minutes from 1912 to 1930. This bound volume provides the only documentation of IFC activities during that period. The "Background Information" folder provides more recent history, and the "Constitution and Bylaws" folder contains several different versions of the constitution. The IFC's heavy involvement in Rush is reflected in the four folders on the subject, and include materials on Dry Rush, a program initiated in the late 1980s. Also of interest are the "Fraternity Membership Statistics" folder, containing statistical data dating to the 1870s, although the bulk of data is from 1960 to 1985, and the "Neighborhood Relations" folder, documenting fraternity house relations with the Ann Arbor community.
  - Alcohol Awareness Week 1985-1993, undated (Box 2)
  - Alcohol Policies, ca. early 1990s (Box 2)
  - Articles of Incorporation 1972-1977, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Background Information on IFC 1966, 1984-1989, undated (Box 2)
  - Committee Restructuring, ca. late 1980s early 1990s (Box 2)
  - Composite Picture Evaluations 1983 (Box 2)
  - Compufair 1985, 1987, undated (Box 2)
  - Constitution and Bylaws 1963, 1967, 1986, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1983-1992 (Box 2)
  - Executive Board Roster 1986, 1991-1993 (Box 2)
  - Fraternity Alumni Meetings 1984-1985 (Box 2)
  - Fraternity Census Forms 1991 (Box 2)
  - Fraternity Coordinating Council (FCC)
    - General 1972-1979, undated (Box 2)
    - Constitution and Bylaws 1974-1979 (Box 2)
    - Meeting Minutes 1973-1979 (Box 2)
  - Fraternity Membership Statistics 1870-1985 (bulk 1960-1985) (Box 2)
  - Fraternity President Roster 1992-1994 (Box 2)
  - Greek Activities Review Panel (GARP) 1985-1990, undated (Box 2)
  - Greek Leadership Conference 1991-1993 (Box 2)
  - Greek Sexual Awareness Day 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Greek Task Force 1985-1989, undated (Box 2)
  - Greek Week 1984, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Hazing Policy 1981, 1985, undated (Box 2)
  - Hectorians 1984-1991 (Box 2)
  - Housing Code and Regulations 1984-1986, undated (Box 2)
  - IFC Coordinator's Update 1990-1994 (Box 2)
  - Intramural Point Structure 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Freshman Council 1985 (Box 2)
  - Mid-America Interfraternity Council Association (MIFCA) 1984-1986 (Box 2)
  - Minutes from IFC Meetings
    - 1912-1930 (Box 2)
      (bound volume, also contains proposed constitution, 1914 articles of agreement; delegate report from Interfraternity Conference, 1924)
    - 1983-1988 (Box 2)
    - 1990-1992 (Box 2)
  - National Interfraternity Conference, ca. early 1990s, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Neighborhood Relations
    - North Burns Park Association (NBPA) 1985-1986 (Box 2)
    - Noisy Party Task Force 1991-1992 (Box 2)
  - Newsclippings 1984-1992, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Order of Omega 1984-1991 (Box 3)
  - Parking Ordinance 1982 (Box 3)
  - Philanthropic Projects 1982-1983 (Box 3)
  - President's Forum 1989-1990 (Box 3)
  - Recognition Petitions for Fraternities circa 1980s (Box 3)
  - Residence Hall Relations 1984 (Box 3)
  - Rush
    - General 1967-1970, 1984-1993 (Box 3)
    - Dry Rush 1986-1991 (Box 3)
    - Recruitment Rules 1988-1994, undated (Box 3)
    - Rush Workshops 1984-1990 (Box 3)
  - Scholarship Fund circa 1970s, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Student Government Council-IFC-Panhel Agreement circa 1960s, 1961-1970 (Box 3)
  - Summer Orientation Program 1985 (Box 3)
  - Target Campus Program 1991-1992 (Box 3)
  - University Council 1970, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
  - Workshops, ca. 1970s-80s 1982-1993, undated (Box 3)
  - Zoning and Planning circa 1980s, undated (Box 3)
- Photographs circa 1980-1994
  The Photographs series (.2 linear feet) covers the late 1980s and early 1990s, and consists mainly of exterior shots of fraternity houses. Also documented are various Greek Week activities from 1988 to 1991.
  - Fraternity Houses, exterior shots circa 1980s-1990s, 35 negatives black and white; 72 photographs color; 15 photographs black and white (Box 3)
  - Greek Week Activities 1988-1991 (Box 3)